<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><mycoreobject xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ID="domlib_institution_00000219" label="domlib_institution_00000219" version="2.0" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="datamodel-institution.xsd"><structure/><metadata xml:lang="de"><names class="MCRMetaLangText" heritable="false" notinherit="false"><name xml:lang="en" inherited="0" form="plain">ˀƎnda Maryam Qorrar / EMQ</name>
</names>
<altnames class="MCRMetaLangText" heritable="false" notinherit="false"><altname xml:lang="en" inherited="0" form="plain">Däbrä Mädḫanit Qorrar</altname>
<altname xml:lang="en" inherited="0" form="plain">Maryam Qorrar</altname>
</altnames>
<visitdates class="DLDateInterval" heritable="false" notinherit="false"><visitdate xml:lang="en" inherited="0"><from>2012-05-12</from><to>2012-05-12</to></visitdate>
</visitdates>
<descbys class="MCRMetaLangText" heritable="false" notinherit="false"><descby xml:lang="en" inherited="0" form="plain">D.N.</descby>
</descbys>
<countries class="MCRMetaLangText" heritable="false" notinherit="false"><country xml:lang="en" inherited="0" form="plain">Ethiopia</country>
</countries>
<areas class="MCRMetaLangText" heritable="false" notinherit="false"><area xml:lang="en" inherited="0" form="plain">Tәgray</area>
</areas>
<towns class="MCRMetaLangText" heritable="false" notinherit="false"><town xml:lang="en" inherited="0" form="plain">wäräda Dägˁa Tämben, ṭabiya Särät, qušät ˀƎnda Maryam Qorrar</town>
</towns>
<latitudes class="MCRMetaNumber" heritable="false" notinherit="false"><latitude xml:lang="en" inherited="0">13.5813</latitude>
</latitudes>
<longitudes class="MCRMetaNumber" heritable="false" notinherit="false"><longitude xml:lang="en" inherited="0">39.123767</longitude>
</longitudes>
<altitudes class="MCRMetaNumber" heritable="false" notinherit="false"><altitude xml:lang="en" inherited="0">2655.0</altitude>
</altitudes>
<foundationdates class="MCRMetaISO8601Date" heritable="false" notinherit="false"><foundationdate inherited="0">1300</foundationdate>
</foundationdates>
<foundtodates class="MCRMetaISO8601Date" heritable="false" notinherit="false"><foundtodate inherited="0">1400</foundtodate>
</foundtodates>
<txfndates class="MCRMetaLangText" heritable="false" notinherit="false"><txfndate xml:lang="en" inherited="0" form="plain">During the reign of King ˁAmdä Ṣəyon I (r. 1314-44).</txfndate>
</txfndates>
<founders class="MCRMetaLangText" heritable="false" notinherit="false"><founder xml:lang="en" inherited="0" form="plain">According to local tradition the monastery was founded by monk Yämanä ˀAb, under King ˁAmdä Ṣəyon I (r. 1314-44).</founder>
</founders>
<conditions class="MCRMetaLangText" heritable="false" notinherit="false"><condition xml:lang="en" inherited="0" form="plain">Gädam. At least 25 monks live in the community; there is a  well-established church school. A more recent church dedicated to Täklä Haymanot, associated with the monastery, is located in the vicinity.&#13;
Tabots (6?): Mary Zion (?), Kidanä Məḥrät, Iyäsus, Four Living Creatures, George, separately one tabot of ˁAbiyä ˀƎgziˀ was mentioned.</condition>
</conditions>
<descriptions class="MCRMetaLangText" heritable="false" notinherit="false"><description xml:lang="en" inherited="0" form="plain">85 Mss. photographed, 1 scroll, objects: 86 Mss. photographed; 1 scroll, objects: EMQ-001 “Miracles of Mary”; EMQ-002 “Psalter”; EMQ-003 “Miracles of Mary”; EMQ-004 “The Book of Hawi”; EMQ-005 “Four Gospel”; EMQ-006 “Vita of Gäbrä Mänfäs Qǝddus”; EMQ-007 “Mǝˁraf”; EMQ-008 “Psalter”; EMQ-009 “Psalter”; EMQ-010 “Order of the Church; Spiritual Medicine”; EMQ-011 “Vita of Filpos”; EMQ-012 “The Book of the Hystory of Giyorgis Wäldä ˁAmid”; EMQ-013 “Psalter; Images of the Picture”; EMQ-014 “The Book of the Spiritual Elder”; EMQ-015 “The Organ of Mary”;E MQ-016 “Image of Mary; Miracles of Mary”; EMQ-017 “Pauline Epistles”; EMQ-018 “The Rite of the Passion Week”; EMQ-019 “The law of the Kings”; EMQ-020 “The Book of the Spiritual Elder”; EMQ-021 “Vision of Isaiah”; EMQ-022 “Miracles of Jesus”; EMQ-023 “Vita of Täklä Haymanot”; EMQ-024 “Five Pillars of Mystery; Vita of Marqos; Praise of the Beloved One; Horologium of the Night”; EMQ-025 “The Harp of Praise”; EMQ-026 “Psalter”; EMQ-027 “Psalter”; EMQ-028 “The Rite of the Passion Week”; EMQ-029 “Psalter”; EMQ-030 “Collection of various texts”; EMQ-031 “Psalter”; EMQ-032 “Psalter”; EMQ-033 “Homily of the Four Beast”; EMQ-034 “Deggwa for Lent”; EMQ-035 “Missal”; EMQ-036 “Zǝmmare”; EMQ-037 “Gospel of John”; EMQ-038 “Praise to God; Image of Christ”; EMQ-039 “Vita of Gäbrä Mänfäs Qǝddus”; EMQ-040 “Mar Yeshaq”; EMQ-041 “The Loosening of Speles”; EMQ-042 “Gospel of John”; EMQ-043 “Mäwasǝˁt”; EMQ-044 “Deggwa for Lent”; EMQ-045 “Psalter”; EMQ-046 “Gospel of John”; EMQ-047 “Vita Gäbrä Krǝstos; Vita of ˀArägawi; Gädlä Pantälewon; Gädlä  Kiros”; EMQ-048 “Miracles of Mary”; EMQ-049 “Homily on St. Michael”; EMQ-050 “Miracles of Mary”; EMQ-051 “Psalter”; EMQ-052 “The Sword of the Trinity”; EMQ-053 “Collection of prayers”; EMQ-054 “Collection of prayers”; EMQ-055 “The Faith of the Fathers”; EMQ-056 “The Collection of Images”; EMQ-057 “Sinodos”; EMQ-058 “The Faith of the Fathers”; EMQ-059 “Homily of Zion; Book of the Cock; Lamentation of Mary; Homily by Ephrem on the Passions of Our Lord”; EMQ-060 “ˀAryam and other texts”; EMQ-061 “I bow to you Divinity...; Image of the Savious of the World”; EMQ-062 “The Rite of Passion Week”; EMQ-063 “Psalter”; EMQ-064 “Psalter”; EMQ-065 “Psalter”; EMQ-066 “The Disciples and other texts”; EMQ-067 “Collection of magic texts”; EMQ-068 “Psalter”; EMQ-069 “Vita of St. George”; EMQ-070 “Praise of God”; EMQ-071 “Psalter”; EMQ-072 “Collection of Hymns”; EMQ-073 “Psalter”; EMQ-074 “The Book of Sirak and other texts”; EMQ-075 “The Books of the Monks”; EMQ-076 “The Book of Cyril”; EMQ-077 “Five Pillars of Mystery”; EMQ-078 “Psalter”; EMQ-079 “Hymns”; EMQ-080 “Five Pillars of Mystery”; EMQ-081 “Deggwa for Lent”; EMQ-082 “Monastic Ritual”; EMQ-083 “The Disciples”; EMQ-084 “The Fortress of the Cross”; EMQ-085 “Psalter”; EMQ-086 “The Loosening of Spells”.</description>
</descriptions>
</metadata><service><servdates class="MCRMetaISO8601Date"><servdate inherited="0" type="createdate">2012-06-29T10:04:16.021Z</servdate><servdate inherited="0" type="modifydate">2015-07-15T08:16:10.241Z</servdate></servdates><servflags class="MCRMetaLangText"><servflag xml:lang="en" inherited="0" form="plain" type="creator">DNosnitsin</servflag><servflag xml:lang="en" inherited="0" form="plain" type="editor">DNosnitsin</servflag></servflags><servacls class="MCRMetaAccessRule"><servacl permission="deletedb"><condition format="xml"><boolean operator="and"><boolean operator="or"><condition field="group" operator="=" value="admingroup"/><condition field="group" operator="=" value="ethioadmins"/></boolean><boolean operator="true"/><boolean operator="true"/></boolean></condition></servacl><servacl permission="read"><condition format="xml"><boolean operator="true"/></condition></servacl><servacl permission="writedb"><condition format="xml"><boolean operator="and"><boolean operator="or"><condition field="group" operator="=" value="admingroup"/><condition field="group" operator="=" value="ethioleaders"/></boolean><boolean operator="true"/><boolean operator="true"/></boolean></condition></servacl></servacls></service></mycoreobject>